DÉBORAH A. MARTÍNEZ FERNÁNDEZ

POLITICAL SCIENCE, DATA ANALYSIS AND GLOBAL ENVIRONMENTAL GOVERNANCE

SUMMARY

Current master's student of Political Science, specializing in Global Environmental Governance, Sustainability, and Climate Change. Previous experience in both quantitative and qualitative research methodologies, with expertise in data analysis and survey analysis both in field and result's interpretation. Experienced in leading teams, conducting fieldwork research, and managing stakeholder relationships. Current main research regarding Global Environmental Governance and particularly climate aid to developing countries.

EDUCATION

Master of Science in Political Science (MSc)

Amsterdam, Netherlands | September 2023 - July 2024

Specialization in Global Environmental Governance, Sustainability, and Climate Change

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam (VU)

Text Mining with R Online | 2021

Github Curse

Cutting-edge Data Analysis Techniques for Political Science

Mexico City, Mexico | 2018

Instituto Tecnológico Autónomo de México (ITAM)

Bachelor's degree in Political Science

Mexico City, Mexico | 2012 – 2018

Instituto Tecnológico Autónomo de México (ITAM)

Dissertation title: "Relationship between corruption and economic growth, from a theoretical and qualitative perspective"

Advisor: Dr. Alberto Simpser Mondlak

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- Facilitated student session on "Financial System through a Lens of Equity and Justice" at Master's program at VU.
- Provided empowerment workshops for rural women in Mexico through Enlace Rural CSO from 2016 to 2017, covering legal and political skills, entrepreneurship, among others.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

- Investigating the levers and barriers impacting economic growth within developing nations.
- Analyzing the allocation of climate aid to the Global South through a lens of equity and justice.
- Exploring avenues for global cooperation to effectively combat climate change.
- Examining the political representation and role of indigenous communities in biodiversity conservation.

SKILLS

- Data Storytelling
- Programming in R
- Data Gathering and Visualization
- Statistical Analysis
- Global Environmental Governance and Sustainability

- Social Science Research Methods
- Network Analysis
- Problem-solving and Decision-making
- Project Management
- Stakeholder Management
- Adaptability and Creativity

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Consultant

MORANT Consultants

Mexico City | January 2022 to September 2023

- Led a team focused on creating solutions using qualitative and quantitative analysis.
- Oversaw survey development, conducted fieldwork research.
- Head of data department for electoral campaigns in Estado de Mexico and Chiapas, México.

Junior Consultant

MORANT Consultants

Mexico City | January 2019 to December 2021

- Coordinated qualitative data collection projects with the Ministry of Education.
- Served as a dialogue coordinator between Colombia's National Federation of Departments and justice system representatives.

LANGUAGE PROFICIENCY

Spanish: Native

• English: Advanced (TOEFL iBT: 101 points)